A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, Office of Reports, Office Files of Richard Magat FA690
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, Office of Reports, Office Files of Richard Magat
1952-1992, bulk 1952-1979
1952-1979
Rockefeller Archive Center
Magat, Richard
Ford Foundation
FA690
7.3 Cubic Feet 3 record storage boxes, 4 LTR size Hollinger boxes, and 3 LGL size Hollinger boxes
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Ford Foundation archive was deposited at RAC in 2011. Ford Foundation records, correspondence, reports, program files and officers papers were transferred to, and accessioned by, RAC beginning in 2011. Accessions continue as necessary.
An additional group of Richard Magat office files was transferred to the RAC by the Ford Foundation in 2018 and was ingested by the RAC as Accession 2018:061. This accession was incorporated into the collection during processing in 2018.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC.
Arrangement
Arranged in 4 series by file type.
Original order has been retained.
Collection arrangement is as follows:
Series 1. Chronological Correspondence, 1974-1979
Series 2. Memoranda and Publications, 1967-1973
Series 3. Publications, 1964-1992
Series 4. Subject Files, 1952-1980
Scope and Contents
Contains correspondence, memoranda, publications and subject files.
Collection consists of more than one accession of Richard Magat office files ingested by the RAC over the years. An accession processed in 2018 consisted of a group of subject files regarding different press, publications, and public relations topics and was added to the end of the Subject Files series in order to reconstitute the relationship between the materials.
The RAC holds another Ford Foundation, Office of Reports, Office Files of Richard Magat collection. A more deliberate collection arrangement appears to have been imposed on this set of material during processing. Therefore, it was decided not to integrate the 2018 accession with that collection or to merge the two collections together. The finding aid for FA728 of Ford Foundation, Office of Reports, Office Files of Richard Magat can be accessed here.
Biographical / Historical
The Ford Foundation was chartered by Henry and Edsel Ford in 1936 "to receive and administer funds for scientific, educational and charitable purposes, all for the public welfare", and initially served the Ford family's charitable interests in the Detroit area. Following the deaths of Edsel Ford (1943) and Henry Ford (1947), the Foundation was propelled to the forefront of philanthropy as the largest American foundation in terms of both endowment and yearly expenditures, and with an international scope to its major program areas.
During the Foundation's first twenty years its major programs were in international economic development, primary and higher education, educational and public broadcasting, behavioral sciences, civil liberties, urban development, fine arts and the humanities. The Ford Foundation also partnered with the Rockefeller Foundation in supporting agricultural development in South America, Africa, and Southeast Asia. Since the 1970s, the Foundation has also pioneered programs in women's rights, energy policy, micro-financing in under-developed countries, establishing human rights groups, and improving international HIV/AIDS education.
Biographical / Historical
Richard Magat was a member of the Ford Foundation staff from 1957 until 1982. Throughout his career at the Foundation Mr. Magat worked in the Office of Reports. He held the following positions:
April 1957, Writer
October 1957, Program Assistant
May 1958, Director
March 1968, Director and Editor
January 1982, Director (part time)
As Director and Editor, Mr. Magat was responsible for: preparing press releases, writing notes to editors and drafting letters to congressmen; writing and editing Foundation publications and articles including the Annual Report, Current Interests, and Ford Foundation Letter; recommending public reports on Foundation activity; responding to media inquiries and arranging press conferences; and administering the Office of Reports.
Mr. Magat also held the following positions:
1947-51, Dayton Daily News, Ohio, The Binghamton Sun, New York, Reporter
1951-52, McGraw-Hill Book Company, Editor in Technical Writing Service
1952-53, Paramount News, Script Writer
1953-57, New York University, Senior News Writer, Office of Information Services
1967, Mayor's Advisory Panel on Decentralization of NYC Schools, Special Assistant
1969, SUNY (Mount Vernon) Cooperative College, Instructor
1975, Joint Committee for the Reappraisal of the Role of the Red Cross, Editor
1979, SUNY (New York) Fashion Institute of Technology, Instructor
Mr. Magat was born January 1, 1927. He received his A.B. degree in 1947 from New York University. Mr. Magat took additional courses at Columbia University, New York University and the New School. Mr. Magat is the author of Ford Foundation at Work, New York: Plenum (1979), and As Others See Us, Geneva: Henry Dumant Institute (1975). He also wrote articles for Saturday Review, Consumer Reports, Trans-action and other magazines and journals. Mr. Magat left the Ford Foundation in September 1982 to become President of the Edward W. Hazen Foundation.
Ford Foundation; Education; Endowments -- Public relations -- United States
- Chronological Correspondence, 1974-1979; I
  - 1974 Chronological Correspondence, 1974 January-June (Box 1)
  - 1974 Chronological Correspondence, 1974 July-December (Box 1)
  - 1975 Chronological Correspondence, 1975 January-June (Box 1)
  - 1975 Chronological Correspondence, 1975 July-December (Box 1)
  - 1976 Chronological Correspondence, 1976 January-June (Box 1)
  - 1976 Chronological Correspondence, 1976 July-December (Box 1)
  - 1977 Chronological Correspondence, 1977 January-June (Box 1)
  - 1977 Chronological Correspondence, 1977 July-December (Box 1)
  - 1978 Chronological Correspondence, 1978 January-June (Box 1)
  - 1978 Chronological Correspondence, 1978 July-December (Box 1)
  - 1979 Chronological Correspondence, 1979 January-June (Box 1)
  - 1979 Chronological Correspondence, 1979 July-December (Box 1)
- Memoranda and Publications, 1967-1973; II
  - Richard Magat Memoranda (1/2), 1967-1970 (Box 2)
  - Richard Magat Memoranda (2/2), 1967-1970 (Box 2)
  - Current Comment on the Ford Foundation (1/2), 1970 April-1973 September (Box 2)
  - Current Comment on the Ford Foundation (2/2), 1970 April-1973 September (Box 2)
- Publications, 1964-1992; III
  - Current Comment on the Ford Foundation, 1974 March-1975 February (Box 3)
  - Current Comment on the Ford Foundation (last copy do not remove), 1974 November (Box 3)
  - Current Comment on the Ford Foundation, 1976 March-1981 May (Box 3)
  - Newspaper Feature Articles and Other Comments Re: Ford Foundation, 1964 January 15-1966 August 15 (Box 3)
  - Editorial Comment on Fourth Installment of "Tax-Exempt Foundations and Charitable Trusts: Their Impact on our Economy" (Wright Patman, December 21, 1966), 1966-1967 (Box 3)
  - Office of Reports -- Editorials, Selected Newspaper Feature Articles, and Other Comments about the Ford Foundation Received Since 1970 (Box 3)
  - Ford Foundation Annual Report Supplements and Excerpts -- Education and Public Policy (1981) and Education and Culture (1982-1983), 1981-1983 (Box 3)
  - Ford Foundation Annual Report Excerpts -- The Arts Program, 1978-1981 (Box 3)
  - Ford Foundation Annual Report Excerpts -- International Affairs, 1984-1987 (Box 3)
  - Ford Foundation Annual Report Excerpts -- Education and Culture, 1984-1992 (Box 3)
- Subject Files, 1952-1980; IV
  Scope and Contents
  Series contains subject files Richard Magat created and maintained to document the Office of Report's work with various press, publications, and public relations projects and issues.
  The most prevalent material formats found within the series are press clippings, correspondence, pamphlets, reports, tables and charts, notes, and publication mock-ups.
  - "The Ford Foundation and Noncommercial Television" -- Rewrite of PBL-NET Factsheet, 1967-1968 (Box 4)
  - Ford Foundation Building -- Press Arrangements, Coverage, Releases, and Fact Sheets Re: Ford Foundation Building and Dedication (1/2), 1967 (Box 4)
  - Ford Foundation Building -- Press Arrangements, Coverage, Releases, and Fact Sheets Re: Ford Foundation Building and Dedication (2/2), 1967 (Box 4)
  - Foundations Case Research Material Re: Foundation Supported Projects, Assorted Foundations, etc., 1963-1964 (Box 4)
  - Newton -- School Improvement Program -- R. Seaver, 1964 (Box 4)
  - New Building --Building Specs, Factsheets (incl. information on garden), Press Releases, Dedication Materials, etc. -- R. Seaver, 1967 (Box 5)
  - Patman Report on Tax-Exempt Foundations, Reports Re: Ford Foundation Finances and Private Foundations, 1963-1966 (Box 5)
  - School Improvement Program -- Individual City Reports for Ford Foundation Report, 1965-1977 (Box 5)
  - Tutorial Community Project -- Book -- Newmark, Jerry [PHOTOS], 1975-1976 (Box 5)
  - Whitman Bassow Carbon File -- Correspondence, Interview Transcripts, Memoranda Re: Foundation Activities, 1969-1970 (Box 5)
  - Whitman Bassow Tape Transcriptions from the Convocation and Groups Re: State of the Ford Foundation and Communication within the Foundation, 1970 (Box 5)
  - Task Forces, 1972-1973 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Grant Guidelines, 1972 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Filer Commission, 1978 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Rockefeller Brothers Fund - Foundation Luncheon Group Panel on New York City Public Schools, 1973-1974 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - International Division - Public relations, 1973-1974 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - International Affairs Program, 1955-1967 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - International Training and Research Program, 1959-1966 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Latin America, 1960-1963 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Medicine - Including mental health, 1958-1959 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - National Merit Scholarship, 1956-1962 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Population, 1954-1969 (Box 6, Folder 11-12)
  - Overseas Development Program, 1958-1979 (Box 7, Folder 13-16)
  - Learning About Learning Task Force, 1972-1973 (Box 8, Folder 17-20)
  - Newman report - Report on Higher Education, 1971 March (Box 8, Folder 21)
  - Nicholas Von Hoffman, 1977 December (Box 8, Folder 22)
  - Non-program gifts - Wayside Inn and Detroit Museum of Art Founders Society, 1958-1959 (Box 8, Folder 23)
  - Presidential announcements, 1956-1979 (Box 8, Folder 24)
  - Operation Philanthropy, 1957-1964 (Box 8, Folder 25-26)
  - Publications - Possible future, 1960-1966; File contains a mock-up of a Ford Foundation booklet that is in fragile condition. Materials attached to the mock-up with adhesives have come loose. (Box 9, Folder 27)
  - Publications - Handling and distribution, 1959-1969 (Box 9, Folder 28)
  - Publications - Reprint series, 1958-1968 (Box 9, Folder 29)
  - Publications - General, including schedules and inventories, 1952-1974 (Box 9, Folder 30)
  - Publications - Country pamphlets, 1964-1970 (Box 9, Folder 31)
  - Annual Report - Action Control Records (ARs), 1953-1958 (Box 9, Folder 32)
  - Proposed formal quarterly - Dummies and outlines, 1955-1967; Mock-ups in file are in fragile condition. Materials attached to the items with adhesives have come loose. (Box 9, Folder 33)
  - The Fund for the Advancement of Education (TFAE) publications, 1958-1962 (Box 9, Folder 34)
  - Reprints of speeches, 1961 (Box 9, Folder 35)
  - A Resource in Jeopardy report, 1969; Sections attached to the document by adhesives are coming loose. (Box 9, Folder 36)
  - School finance, 1974 (Box 9, Folder 37)
  - School finance - Political Economy of Education Conference, Silverado, California, 1973-1975 (Box 10, Folder 38)
  - Staff speech - Is Education Worth It? by Harold Howe, 1980 (Box 10, Folder 39)
  - Travel and Study Awards, 1964 September 1 (Box 10, Folder 40)
  - U.S. Treasury Department Report on Private Foundations, 1964-1966 (Box 10, Folder 41)
  - Resolutions, 1979 (Box 10, Folder 42)
  - United Nation Development Corporation (UNDC), 1967-1969 (Box 10, Folder 43)
  - Urban Affairs, 1957-1963 (Box 10, Folder 44)
  - Vocational education, undated (Box 10, Folder 45)
  - Yale University - Pay as You Earn (PAYE), 1971 (Box 10, Folder 46)
  - Yale University - Pay as You Earn (PAYE), 1970-1971 (Box 10, Folder 47)